<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-13T17:06:10+00:00</updated><id>https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Anshul Singh, M.Sc. Mathematics student at IIT Delhi. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Geometry of Uncertainty: What Missing Data Teaches Us About Truth</title><link href="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2026/uncertainty-structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Geometry of Uncertainty: What Missing Data Teaches Us About Truth"/><published>2026-01-08T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-08T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2026/uncertainty-structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2026/uncertainty-structure/"><![CDATA[<p>We often assume that knowledge is defined by what we can see, measure and record. In mathematics, we find comfort in the defined: the closed set, the converged sequence, the observed variable. But in my recent research work on <em>Reliability Theory</em> and <em>Middle Censoring</em>, I have learned that the most critical information often lies in what is <em>absent</em>.</p> <h3 id="the-paradox-of-censoring">The Paradox of Censoring</h3> <p>In statistical analysis, we often deal with “censored” data instances where we know a component started functioning and perhaps know when the experiment ended, but the actual moment of failure is lost to us. We have the <em>start</em> and the <em>end</em>, but the <em>event</em> is hidden in the interval. A novice might throw this data away, viewing it as “incomplete.” A statistician knows better. We know that the silence is not empty; it is informative. The fact that the component <em>survived</em> up to a certain point tells us something profound about its strength, even if we never saw it break.</p> <h3 id="bayesian-beliefs-in-a-noisy-world">Bayesian Beliefs in a Noisy World</h3> <p>This mathematical framework mirrors a deeper philosophical reality. We rarely have “perfect data” in life. We navigate careers, relationships and scientific discovery with middle censored or missing information. We see the inputs and the outputs, but the internal mechanisms often remain a “black box.” This is where the <strong>Bayesian</strong> perspective becomes a philosophy of life, not just a method of inference. It teaches us to start with a <em>prior</em>—a belief based on past experience and update it as we encounter the world. It is a mathematical admission of humility: we never know the absolute truth, we only refine our approximation of it.</p> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>As I worked on formulating methodologies for these kind of problems, I am reminded that our goal is not to eliminate uncertainty that is impossible. Our goal is to map the geometry of that uncertainty. To be a statistician is to be comfortable in the dark, using the faint signals of probability to construct a map of a world we can never fully see.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="Statistics"/><category term="Philosophy"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A reflection on Middle Censoring, Bayesian priors and the philosophical weight of the unobserved]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Geometry of Silence: Five Days on the Kedarkantha Trek</title><link href="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2024/kedarkantha-trek/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Geometry of Silence: Five Days on the Kedarkantha Trek"/><published>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2024/kedarkantha-trek</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anshulsingh-web.github.io/blog/2024/kedarkantha-trek/"><![CDATA[<p>In December 2024, I traded the dense fog of Delhi for the crisp, biting air of the <em>Garhwal Himalayas</em>. I undertook the five day trek with my friend to Kedarkantha summit (12,500 ft).</p> <p>In our hyper connected world, the most terrifying aspect wasn’t the altitude or the sub zero temperatures; it was the certainty that past the village of Sankri, my phone would become a useless brick of glass and lithium. Five days with zero connectivity. No emails, no weather updates, no infinite social media scroll. What happens when an analytical mind, trained in statistics and mathematics, is abruptly cut off from the data stream and dropped into a stark, indifferent landscape of snow and rock?</p> <p>It turns out, when the digital noise fades, the world reveals its underlying structure in clearer, often harsher, terms.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-optimization-problem-of-ascent">The Optimization Problem of Ascent</h2> <p>The trek began through pine forests, the trail already dusted with snow. As a mathematics student, I couldn’t help but view the path not just as scenery, but as a complex optimization problem 🙂. Every step is a real time calculation of energy expenditure versus elevation gain. The trail is rarely linear; it is a continuous series of varying gradients. My body became a machine trying to solve for efficiency on a steep slope. You learn very quickly that the shortest distance between two points (a straight line up) is often the most inefficient path in energy terms. You have to respect the curve, the switchback the geometry dictates your pace.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/trek_forest.jpg" alt="The trail"/> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The path is rarely linear. Navigating the initial gradients through the pine forests. </div> <h2 id="statistics-of-the-sky">Statistics of the Sky</h2> <p>Without a weather app to give me a neat percentage chance of precipitation, I was forced back into a primal state of statistical inference. Nature provides a constant stream of raw data, unsupervised. The sampling points were everywhere: the shift in wind direction, the specific density of the clouds gathering over the distant peaks, the temperature drop as the sun dipped behind a ridge.</p> <p>My brain was furiously performing Bayesian updates. Every new sensory input updated my prior belief about the probability of a snowstorm. It was a stark reminder that statistics began not in spreadsheets, but in survival in the human need to predict uncertain outcomes in a stochastic environment.</p> <h2 id="the-celestial-dataset">The Celestial Dataset</h2> <p>At night, far above the light pollution of the plains, the sky revealed itself not as a void, but as a dense, overwhelming view.</p> <p>It was a “Starry Night” view, but stripped of Van Gogh’s swirling impressionism and replaced with cold, hard precision. The density of stars felt statistically improbable. Seeing the Milky Way stretch across the horizon was like looking at a high dimensional manifold projected onto a 2D sphere. It is a sight that silences the ego; a reminder that our terrestrial mathematics is just a localized attempt to describe a universally vast system.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/trek_night.jpg" alt="Starry night"/> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A long exposure of the Himalayan night sky. A celestial dataset untouched by light pollution. </div> <h2 id="the-philosophy-of-the-summit-push">The Philosophy of the Summit Push</h2> <p>The summit day started at 2:00 AM in bone chilling darkness. This is where mathematics gives way to philosophy, specifically Stoicism. The physical discomfort of climbing steep inclines in knee deep snow at -10°C is immense. The “why” of it becomes deafening. Why endure this voluntary suffering just to stand on a peak and immediately walk down?</p> <blockquote> <p>“The struggle itself toward the heights is enough to fill a man’s heart. One must imagine Sisyphus happy.” — Albert Camus</p> </blockquote> <p>Camus might call it absurd. But in the moment, it felt deeply existential. There is a profound clarity that comes with physical exhaustion in a frozen landscape. You are reduced to the immediate reality of the next breath and the next step. The mountain is indifferent to your struggle; it demands endurance.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/trek_summit.jpg" alt="The summit"/> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The summit at 12,500 ft. The view that makes the absurd effort rational. </div> <p>Reaching the summit as the sun broke over the Yamunotri and Gangotri ranges was a moment of pure geometric awe. The view is a fractal landscape peaks repeating upon peaks in self similar patterns stretching into infinity. It is a humbling reminder of scale. In the face of such geological vastness, our daily statistical worries seem vanishingly small.</p> <h2 id="the-zero-data-void">The Zero Data Void</h2> <p>Returning to Sankri after five days felt like waking from a deep meditative state. When my phone finally caught a signal and began buzzing with five days of accumulated notifications, I felt a distinct sense of loss.</p> <p>The silence of the Kedarkantha had been filled with a richer kind of data the crunch of snow, the rhythm of breath and the undeniable logic of the mountain. It was a powerful reminder that while our models and theorems help us understand the world, sometimes you just have to walk the terrain to truly grasp its reality.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Two things fill the mind with ever new and increasing admiration and awe, the more often and steadily we reflect upon them: <strong>the starry heavens above me and the moral law within me.</strong>”</p> <p>— <strong>Immanuel Kant</strong>, <em>Critique of Practical Reason</em></p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="Experience"/><category term="Trekking"/><category term="Philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A December summit push without internet, viewed through the lens of math, stats and existential philosophy.]]></summary></entry></feed>